This is the first in a series of videos on the xv6
operating system kernel.
This is a very short but very sweet Unix-like operating system
that's used for educational purposes.
It was developed at MIT and used to other places as well.
This is an operating system that's used by students primarily in an operating system course.
And there are two implementations of this kernel.
One for the x86 architecture
and one for the RISC-V architecture.
In this series of videos I'm going to be talking about the RISC-V version.
The RISC-V version that is used is a 64 bit processor
and whether using the x86 version or the RISC-V version,
you're probably
going to be using it in an emulated fashion
using an emulator like QEMU.
Most likely you don't have a spare computer sitting around.
Probably a spare
RISC-V processor is even less likely.
So
instead, you'll be running the operating system if you choose to run it
under an emulator.
But in any case, it's meant to run on a bear machine
and in fact, it's a multi core operating system.
So, QEMU is capable of emulating multi core systems.
As I said, it's short and very sweet.
It's only about 6000 lines of code.
Most of it is written in the C programming language
with maybe about 300 lines in assembly language.
In this video series, what I'm going to do is
do a walk through of more or less all of the code
to give you an idea of what's going on with it.
The code is very simple and
well written and clean code
and I've read a lot of C code and written a lot of C code
and I'm still learning new coding techniques.
And I think this is an example
that is worth studying.
In addition, of course
as an operating system kernel
it illustrates some of the basic concepts that you'd be learning
in an operating systems course.
So that's another good reason to study this code in detail.
For this video series,
I'm not going to assume that you have any
knowledge of the RISC-V instruction set architecture,
but I will assume that you have had some assembly language coding.
I intend to walk through the assembly language instructions line by line
so I will hold your hand there, so don't worry.
Have you had an operating system class?
Maybe you're in an operating system class right now that is using the xv6 system.
In any case
I've taught a few operating system classes and
I'll probably go over some of the concepts as we encounter them.
This is going to be a long series
so buckle your seat belts.
It's not for the faint of heart.
I'm assuming that you've got some brains
and for the more I'm assuming that you're
interested in this particular system and can focus for the amount of time that it's going to be
for this video series.
So let's look at some of the features that the kernel has.
It's got processes.
These processes run in their own virtual address spaces,
so there are page tables for
page table for each address space to support the virtual address spaces.
The operating system supports files
Unix-like files and the directory hierarchy.
You can pipe data from one program to another program.
of course
there is a timer interrupt so there is multitasking.
The various processes are running in parallel
with time-slicing.
There are 21 system calls that are implemented in xv6.
This is not a lot
The production Unix systems have more like 300 system calls
maybe 500 system calls but this is enough
to give you the core ideas of Unix.
There are a number of user programs that are supplied with this kernel
and these can illustrate
the capabilities of this operating system.
The operating system can run a simple shell program.
in fact
I made a video that talks about the shell program
in detail, you can look for that if you want.
Other common Unix programs: cat, echo
grep
kill, which is used to terminate a process.
ln, which is used to create a hard link from one file to another
and ls, which is used to list out the contents of a directory.
and ls which is used to list out the contents of a directory.
You can create directories.
You can remove files.
and wc is for counting the words in a file
as well as the characters
so, all in all
I think that this can really be considered
a true Unix system,
although it's pretty short and simple
There's a lot that's missing okay
definitely
all the complexity of a real operating system is not there
a real operating system like Linux may have
you know as much as 100 times as much code
and you know we're talking
a million lines of the kernel
and you know when you add the device drivers in
you can go up to many millions of lines of code, so
this is just too much for any human to study really
and if you want to find out how kernels work
this is really the operating system for you.
But there are some things that are missing from your typical Unix or Linux system.
There are no user IDS and no login sequence, no verification
there are no protection bits associated with files
the read, write, execute protections that's not here
the "mount" command is just not available so
you just have one file system
in a real system
the virtual address spaces can be paged out to disk
so that you can run
more processes than will fit in physical main memory
that's not present in xv6
there's no support for networks, no sockets or anything like that
In fact there's no way for processes to communicate
or synchronize amongst themselves.
There are two device drivers but
a real operating system
a real world operating system is going to have many more device drivers
to support all kinds of different bits of hardware that you might find
and lastly there is only a limited amount of user code.
I listed the approximate 10 programs that are distributed with it
but a real usable Linux or Unix system is gonna have lots and lots of apps
so let's go over some of the
system calls that are present
I'll go over these in more detail later when we encounter them
but I just want to
kind of list them out here so you could see
what we've got
So fork()
these are familiar from any Unix or Linux system
the parameters are slightly different in some cases but
the parameters are slightly different in some cases, but
the idea is there
in
concept anyway
fork() is used to create a new process
wait() is used to
wait for a child process to terminate
exit() is for terminating a process
pipe() is for creating pipes
and then we've got open()
close()
read() and write()
for dealing with files.
We've got kill() to terminate process.
We've got exec(), which is passed a file name and will read in that file
presumably it's an executable file
and we'll load it into memory creating a new virtual address space and execute it.
We can make inodes [ by mknod() ].
We can
create links [ by link() ]
hard links, and we can remove hard links and
unlink files [ by unlink() ]
thereby possibly removing them if it's the last link.
We can get information about files [ by fstat() ].
We can change directories [ by chdir() ].
So, we
do have a notion of the current working directory.
dup() is used for copying file descriptors.
Now, we can get the program ID
sorry the process ID for the current process [by getpid()]
We can grow the heap [ by sbrk() ]
so, that's this function here, this system call here
and we can put a process to sleep for a while [by sleep()]
and we can also see how long the kernel has been running [ by uptime() ].
So in the next videos in this series
I'll be going through the code in quite a bit more detail
but I just want to start with giving you an idea
of what this operating system kernel has,
and what its capabilities are.
So, you can determine whether you want to make the commitment for watching these videos.
As I said, this series is not for the faint of heart
it's not for the amateurs
it's for people who really want to
look at an operating system kernel in detail
and understand
a rather large but not
too large body of code, okay
Let's get started with the next video.