Hi, welcome to another video in a series on the xv6 operating system kernel.
xv6 is an educational kernel,
and in this video,
I am going to talk about some general features of the kernel.
It's meant to run on a shared memory multiprocessor.
In other words,
it's meant to run on a system with multiple cores
but which all share a single range of main memory.
In this video and in the code, I'm going to be using the
terms "CPU", "core" and "hart" synonymously.
So in the code sometimes you see CPU,
sometimes you see hart,
and I tend to say core,
but they all mean a hardware processor
capable of executing a single thread of control.
This term "hart" which stands for hardware thread
is something that
I first encountered when reading the RISC-V documentation.
The idea is normally a core will execute a single hardware thread
but for some high performance cores
you might have
say two hardware threads.
For example
with the Intel Hyper-Threading architectures,
you might have two threads running on a single core.
The idea is that these two threads are being  interwoven, the instructions are being executed
concurrently or possibly interwoven.
In such a way to share some of the processing hardware.
The idea is to increase the performance per transistor,
so this term "hart" appears.
But for our purposes we're going to be running it on system
with multiple cores and so these terms are all synonymous,
there's just a single hardware thread per core.
Okay, main memory is shared.
Sometimes, we call it RAM.
In a real operating system,
the issues (regarding the caching of main memory, L1, L2 and so on,) are important
are important
and the kernel needs to sort of work around the
caching schemes and caching system.
In order to improve performance,
in this kernel
all concerns about caching are completely ignored.
The main memory is 128 megabytes (MB)
and this is just hardwired into the kernel's code.
It's fixed with a "#define".
A typical real world operating system kernel is going to
look at the amount of memory that's available on the machine when it starts up
and it's going to configure itself to use all the physical memory.
But within the xv6
it's just hardwired in with 128 megabytes (MB).
The xv6 system can handle a couple of different devices.
The UART is the device that handles serial communication
This stands for Universal Asynchronous Received/Transmit Unit.
In the old days it was a separate chip,
but now it's integrated on the processor chip along with the cores and so on.
This is the device that provides a communication channel for printing and reading input from a keyboard.
Typically, if you program with the Arduino, you're probably going to be familiar with this.
Essentially, it can send a byte stream
in one direction and receive a byte string
coming back in the other direction.
The xv6 system has one disk drive
and that will be emulated, of course, with the file on your host laptop,
but there's a disk device.
There are also timer interrupts.
The UART and the disk are shared between all the cores,
but each core has its own timer interrupt
so these are local to the core.
Processors in the real world
contain something called a plic or platform level interrupt controller
and what this does is a separate chip or separate circuit
that deals with interrupts coming in from all the different devices that might be on a system
and it's figuring out which core should be interrupted
which core should be told about the interrupt and
allowed to handle the interrupt and deal with it
The emulator will emulate
the platform level interrupt controller
and there's also a core local interrupt controller which is also
part of the emulation
and there is one of these core local interupt controllers
for each core.
So the operating system has to deal with these things as well.
Memory management is pretty simple.
Memory physical memory is divided into pages,
and the page size is fixed with the "#define" at 4 kilobytes (KB).
Memory is allocated at least for the kernel from a freelist, there's a freelist of unused pages
and it's a simple link list
and whenever the kernel needs more memory
it allocates the page from the freelist
and when that page is no longer needed
it is returned by adding it to the front of the freelist
very basic memory
allocation scheme
There are no objects in the operating system
in xv6 there are several different structures
and of course they're pointers
but with an object oriented programming language
typically you would be allocating variable sized objects
none of that's going on in a real world kernel
there are other aspects for
there are other
techniques for allocating memory
to accommodate variable sized chunks of memory
but that doesn't happen in xv6
there's no "malloc" for example.
The virtual address spaces are handled with page tables.
The page tables are 3 levels.
I've shown diagrammatically 3 level page table
down at the bottom we have the data pages.
There is one table per process
and in addition, there is one page table for the kernel itself
which maps all of the physical memory
that table for the kernel is shared by all the cores
The page table hardware can accommodate marking the data pages
as either readable, writable, executable
and U stands for user mode access and V stands for valid.
So, a page may or may not be writeable.
It may or may not be executable.
It may or may not be valid.
it can also be marked
you or not you
and that determines whether
the page can be accessed when the processor is running in user mode.
Well, I just use the word processor here
and probably I should say core
so sometimes I guess I use the word processor synonymously with CPU and core.
It shows my age perhaps.
So, some pages
may be restricted
so that they can only be accessed when the core is running in
kernel mode and other pages can be accessed by user mode code.
The scheduler for xv6 is quite simple
it's a basically a round-robin scheduler.
Each process is given a time-slicing and then it goes back
it becomes dormant sitting on the ready queue.
The size of all time slices are fixed.
It happens to be fixed at 1 million cycles.
All the cores share a single ready queue.
Sometimes a ready queue is called a ready list or
a run list or a run queue.
I'll use all those terms probably
but in any case there's only one of these things
Now
the cores share the single ready queue
and so when a core is ready to run a process
it will select a process
the next runnable process from the ready queue
and it will give it a time slice on that core
and then it will
return it to the ready queue after the time slice ends.
and
so this ready queue is actually an array
and what's happening is each core
for scheduling is going through that array linearly
when it gets to the bottom of the array
goes back up to the top
and what it's doing is it's searching for a process
that is runnable
that is it's ready to go
and it's ready for its next time slice
and when it finds one
it gives it a time slice
and then after the time slice ends
It returns it to the ready queue as a runnable
process and moves on to the next process
and so it just keeps going through
each core keeps going through that array repeatedly
and so I said this is a round-robin scheduler
it's not quite round-robin
because what can happen is
particular process might be given a time slice
say on core No. 1
and then after the time slice completes
the core will put it back on the ready queue and
then move on to find another runnable process
but immediately or very soon after, some other core
perhaps core No. 4
might be searching through the array and it might happen to come to
that same process p
and so it will give it a time slice and then
put it back on the ready queue when the time slice ends.
So, what happens is this single process p
might be given a time slice on core No. 1
and then immediately after
given another time slice on core No. 4
and so
normally with round-robin
after process p is given a time slice
it needs to wait until all other
runnable processes have a chance to run
but with xv6
and the multiple cores
it's sort of round-robin within each core
so it's not quite a
proper round-robin scheduling but it's simple
and it's probably just about as effective equally
efficient.
The boot sequence is pretty basic.
The emulator which will be
emulating the RISC-V processor and running our kernel
basically skips all the boot sequence altogether.
What it's going to do is it's going to load the kernel
from some executable file on your host laptop
and it's going to put it into
the memory or I should say the fixed
physical memory that the sorry the emulated
physical memory of the RISC-V processor it's emulating
and it's going to put that
kernel code at a fixed location.
In fact, this is the actual location that it uses.
There's no support in xv6 for booting
a boot loader or a master boot record or
BIOS or anything like that.
This xv6 uses
a couple of techniques for locking and concurrency control.
Spin locks are used
and there are two functions: sleep() and wakeup().
With spin locks you have two functions.
They're called acquire() and release()
and there's a single word in memory
that word is 0 if the lock is free or unheld
and it is 1 if the lock is
busy or is locked, is being held by some process
and what acquire()
will do is just basically in a tight loop
wait for that word
to become 0 unlocked
and then when it finds that it's unlocked
it will set it to 1
and release() just simply sets the word back to 0
sleep() and wakeup()
well when a particular
thread executes the sleep() function
it will end its time slice and it will be
placed back on the ready queue with
a status of runnable
sorry, with a status of not runnable
and it will then sleep until it's
been until it is woken up
so when a process executes the sleep() function
that process will no longer be runnable.
It will go into a blocked or sleep state
and it will not be scheduled
Later, some other process will
execute the wakeup() function and
wake up one or more processes, or 0 or more processes
and if our process happens to get
woken up then it will be changed
back from a status of sleeping or blocked to
runnable and then it will get time slices after that.
There's also a third technique that is sometimes used
and that is the selective disabling of interrupts.
So, each core has a status control word
and there is a bit in that control word that can be either set or cleared
which either enables and allows interrupts or disables and prevents interrupts.
By disabling interrupts
a thread running on one core can prevent being interrupted
when a timer interrupt goes off or when an IO device
calls for an interrupt.
So
we can use this technique on one core to prevent being
interrupted by
another thread on that same core.
However, xv6 is a multi core system
and disabling interrupts on one core has no impact on other cores
so a thread on another core can be modifying memory simultaneously.
xv6 has a number of fixed limits
These are declared with pound sign defines (#define).
For example
the number of processes is just a fixed number.
As I said, the ready queue is stored in an array
and that array is allocated with a fixed size
The number of files open
the maximum number of files that can be opened simultaneously as a fixed number
and so on.
The kernel tends to use arrays and not linked lists so much
and so in several situations we
are running through these arrays with a linear search.
For example, there is a function to kill a process
and it's passed the process ID
and what it does is it does a linear search of the
array of processes.
Actually, this ready queue here is not a separate
data structure.
There's a single array of processes
and some of them are marked runnable, and some of them are
not runnable and so when we
want to find a process that's runnable
we basically just
go through the process array
looking for one that has a status of runnable
and likewise when we want to kill a process
we just run through the array
looking for one that has a matching process ID.
OK, now let me talk about the user address space
so this is the virtual address space that a
user mode program sees
and here I'm showing the address starting at location 0
going up to the maximum virtual address (MAXVA)
The kernel will allocate this address space
in units of pages.
Each one of these is a 4k page
and so, when the exact system call is used, the kernel will
go out to the file system
and find the executable file which is in ELF format
and it will allocate several pages
an integral number of pages here
and it will read in
the data and the code into this region of memory.
Those pages will then be marked read
write and executable by the kernel.
You also have a page allocated for the stack.
We see here that the stack only gets one page
4 kilobytes (KB) of memory
and so xv6 is somewhat limited in this aspect.
A process that wants to grow its stack beyond this will
not be able to
and so xv6 cannot support that
and when a process tries to grow its stack beyond that
it will simply be aborted.
The process will be terminated
and the way the kernel does that is kind of clever
It allocates what is called a guard page right here
This guard page is not readable, not writable.
In fact
it's not accessible in user mode.
So, if the user mode code tries to access this page
its virtual address space
it will immediately cause an exception and the process will be
thrown out and terminated.
The heap
starts after the stack and grows
in units of pages
this is called the brk
If you program in Linux or Unix
you may be familiar with this concept.
As the user mode code allocates things on its heap
this boundary here will be moved up.
The kernel will be invoked to allocate
more pages and the brk point will be moved up
and will consume some of the unused space.
These pages will be marked read and write.
I should say that in a typical Linux or Unix system
the stack is usually put in high memory and it grows down
and it's capable of growing
and memory is only filled up when these two
when the heap and the stack run into each other
that's not done with xv6
we have just a single stack page down here
However, we have something interesting going on.
We have
two pages up at the very top of the virtual memory space
virtual memory happens to be 256 gigabytes (GB)
so this unused space here is actually huge
and the heap may not take up very much of that
and certainly it's not going to take it all up because
we only have 128 megabytes (MB) of physical memory
and we're not going to be able to accommodate
anything larger than that
any virtual address space that exceeds
128 megabytes (MB)
These pages up here are marked not accessible in user mode
so user code cannot access these pages.
User mode cannot
read them or write them or execute any code from them.
These are used during trap and exception processing
so the trampoline page contains code, so it's executable
and when an exception or interrupt occurs
we're going to be executing code in the trampoline page.
We'll discuss that later.
The trap frame
is readable and writeable and that is where the registers will be saved
When a trap that is when an exception or an interrupt occurs
the registers, the entire state of this user process
will be saved and it will be saved in the trap frame
by code in the trampoline page.
There is
each virtual address space has its own trap frame page
so they're all mapped to the same location
but there are different physical memory pages, so each
process has its own trap frame, the trampoline page is shared by all
processes, so the exact same page of
physical memory is mapped into the same spot in all of the virtual address spaces.
One thing I was going to mention was that
I said that the kernel doesn't have a very sophisticated memory allocation system.
It just has
pages and they are kept in a free list
and so all allocations are in
units of one page or 4096 bytes
4K bytes.
However, we accommodate heaps for the user mode programs
so a user mode program is free to implement malloc
and allocate things on the heap
in fact it's free to implement
whatever complex garbage collection algorithm it wants to
but it just has this memory that can be grown here
to allocate its memory to accommodate its memory needs.
so I mentioned that this
"¬u" here means that the guard page is not
valid when it's accessed in user mode
Likewise, the trampoline and trap frame pages are not
accessible in user mode.
C programmers will be familiar with the main function
which takes a couple of arguments argc and argv
and these points are the arguments that are passed into the program when it begins executing.
You may also be familiar with something called arge
for environment
but that is not
accommodated with xv6.
xv6 doesn't
use any environment variables
just argc and argv
and how does that happen
well when an exact system call is made
the code in the kernel will set up the virtual address space here
and among other things
it will allocate a page for the stack
and it will push onto the stack the arguments
we'll get into the details of
exactly what to push later
but basically it's going to push all the arguments
onto the stack
and then set the stack pointer to be
something besides right here
It will allocate these things on the stack
essentially pushing them onto the stack
and moving them into the registers
so when
the first instruction of the user program is executed
it will already find several things on the stack
it will find its the arguments on the stack
now I mentioned that we could only have 256
gigabytes (GB) of virtual address space
I want to
mention that the RISC-V architecture.
It's a pretty complex architecture
and there's several different options
for page tables
there are three options called SV32, SV39, SV48
The version of the architecture being used for xv6
is the SV39 version.
The first one is a two level page table scheme.
The second one is a three level page table scheme and
SV48 is a four level page table scheme
so xv6 uses SV39 architecture which
provides for our three level page tables
okay
and with that particular scheme
virtual addresses are 39 bits
well, 39 bits happens to be
2 to the 39 happens to be 512 gigabytes (GB)
so with this scheme
we could actually access 512 gigabytes (GB)
2 to the 39 expressed in hex is this number here
and so you can see
that expressed down here are 39 bits
and the first bit beyond that would be
in here, right here, 88 is 1000
and then 0, is 000 and so on.
so, it turns out that xv6 only uses 38 bits
okay, it does not use the full 39 bits, it's one bit shy
and so 2 to the 38 is actually 256 gigabytes (GB)
and that number is 40,0000,0000
that is equated to our maximum number
so this our address range is from 0 to
3F
that's 3 is 11 and then F 1111
so 3F
111111 and then  FFFF,FFFF
so our maximum address is this and
so maximum virtual address here is actually
the address of the byte just beyond our virtual address
okay, that's it for this video.
I'll see you on the next one.