This video is part of a series on the xv6
operating system kernel.
In this video, I am going to introduce the main function
and talk a little bit about the startup procedure.
Before that, I'm going to go over the file organization
and I'll end by going over a couple of small files that we can take care of, quickly.
Let's begin with the files that are included with the xv6 system.
Here I've listed out all of the files
so you can see there are not too many of them.
The organization is pretty straightforward.
You've got two directories:
kernel and user.
These are the files that are in the kernel directory
basically it's just a bunch of C code files
some header files.
There are several assembly language files.
There's entry.S which I'll discuss based a little bit
kernelvec.S
There is switch.S, very interesting one
trampoline.S
There's also initcode.S
There's also a file here that's used by the linker as well.
in the user directory, you have
the code for the initial process
as well as the code for the user application programs
the shell
and user mode programs like cat, echo, and so on.
In addition
you've got a makefile to build all these files
and you've got a readme, and a license file
so it's pretty straightforward organization.
This 6th system runs on a multi core computer
and
when it begins
each core will start executing all at once.
They all begin at the same time.
It's a shared memory system
so all cores will share the exact same memory
and they will all begin executing the same exact code
and that code is in a file called entry.S.
It's not a very long file, just a few lines
and that code will then transfer control to a C function called start in the file start.c
and that will then transfer control to the main function.
The assembly code that's in the entry file
basically
gets things set up so that we can execute C programs.
It will initialize the stack pointer register
the SP register
and it will initialize the TP register.
Each core will share main memory, so they will be
accessing the same set of global variables
but each core will need its own stack.
They can't overlap that wouldn't work at all
so
there's a separate stack space for each of the cores
and the code entry.S will
initialize the stack pointer register for the core
appropriately
also
there's a TP register that stands for thread Pointer
but the TP register actually will contain
the core number, the number of the core 0, 1, 2, or so on
instead of some sort of a thread pointer and that
register will stay constant on that core throughout
so that allows the code to ask at any time what core am I running on.
so once those are set up
we transfer control to the start function
In another video
I talk about the different modes that the
RISC-V processor can execute in.
It can execute in machine mode
supervisor mode and user mode.
All of the kernel runs in supervisor mode
except for a tiny bit of code
which is in this start.c file and that so initially when the system begins execution.
It begins executing in machine mode
and the code here will take care of a few bookkeeping things
and then switch to supervisor mode
and the cores will remain in supervisor mode after that
Okay, now let's take a look at the main function.
Here is the code
for main.c
it's not very long and it contains nothing more than the main function
so let's see what happens
remember that
each core will begin executing this code in parallel
so the all cores will begin with this if statement
cpuid() is a short function that basically looks at
and returns the value of the TP register.
So, on core 0 this function will return 0
and core 0 will then execute this code here.
All other cores will execute this code here instead.
So, what does the code do?  Well, core 0 is tasked with initializing things
so you see a lot of calls to init
init this, init that and init some other stuff
It also prints out this message that
the kernel is booting
there is a global variable or
a shared variable here, it's in the memory space
so, of course, all cores will have access to it
and it's used for synchronization
This keyword here, "volatile", is a little bit of
C magic that says that this variable is used for synchronization
possibly by multiple cores or concurrent threads
and it is in fact used to control the beginning of the other cores
so it is initialized to
0 or false if you will
and once core 0 is done initializing, it will change it to
true.
All the other cores
go into this tight loop where they're testing it
and they keep testing until it is found to be true
and then they execute this code here
and they start out by printing
hart something starting.
The term "hart" is synonymous with core
at least for these videos
and so basically saying core 1 is starting
core 2 is starting and so on
and they are pulling up their own call, a cpuid() right here
The last thing that core 0 does is it starts the
code for
the init process so that's what's going on here
and then it sets started to one and then the other
the other cores will do some initialization here.
kvminit
trapinit
plicinit, these are per core initialization things
and they happen in core 0 as well.
kvminit
trapinit
and plicinit happen here for core 0.
Once all of that happens on all of the cores
each core will then call the scheduler() function
and what scheduler() will do?
It will look for a process to execute
so at that point all the cores will start executing
processes
We also see this  __sync_synchronize()
function here.
This is again a little bit of compiler magic
compilers will try to optimize things and what this is doing is telling the compiler
to chill out and not do that optimization.
The compiler might rearrange code in order to
try to achieve greater performance and efficiency.
What the synchronize does is tell the compiler
make sure you finish everything above it first before you start anything after it
so it's saying
please finish all of this initialization
before you change this variable to 1.
You may not be able to understand what I'm doing here.
You're saying to the compiler
but I'm telling you
you need to finish doing
every single thing above this before
you think about changing that variable to 1.
Likewise down here
it's telling the compiler the same thing
don't start executing this stuff
until you have completed this while loop here.
Okay, there are several small files that
I want to take a quick look at
and get these out of the way.
types.h
contains just these typedef here.
You're probably familiar with these abbreviations for familiar types.
So
on the architecture we're using, the RISC-V architecture
with the toolchain
it's a 64 bit machine, integers will be 32 bits.
So, we define
uint8 (unsigned 8 bit) values, uint16 (unsigned 16 bit) values
uint32 (unsigned 32 bit) values and uint64 (unsigned 64 bit) values
We use this type uint64 quite a bit for addresses and pointers.
Okay
next file I want to look at is param.h
There are a number of things that are hard coded into
the kernel, so let me just go through these quickly.
NPROC
the maximum number of processes is just set to 64
the number of cores is 8
and you have other things
the number of open files
the number of open files per system
number of inodes
number of devices
the device number ROOTDEV
MAXARG this is the
maximum number of arguments that you can have on
an exact system call
MAXOPBLOCKS, LOGSIZE, NBUF
FSSIZE, MAXPATH that's the
maximum number of characters in a files path name
Finally, I want to look at a file called defs.h
and this
is
looked it out here on these four pages so
you can see what's going on
but basically this is just for the compiler
contains a bunch of function prototypes, so, for example
the file console.c contains
at least these three functions which might be used
in other files as well
so this is basically
just the function prototypes
there's nothing
much of interest here we'll encounter all these files later, so let's go through all these pages
much of interest here we'll encounter all these files later, so let's go through all these pages.
On the last page, there is
a preprocessor macro.
Perhaps you've seen this in other context
but this is the number of elements and you would have
a variable here and
an array variable
and what it does is (that) it just asks how big is the entire array
and
how big is a single element
and it just gives you the number of elements.
Okay, that's it for this video.
I'll see you in the next video.