This video is part of a series on the xv6
operating system kernel.
In this video
I'm going to describe spin locks
and tell you how they're implemented in the xv6 kernel.
First, let's start off with
remembering what spin locks are.
The idea is that
the spin lock is represented with a single word
and I've called that word "locked" here
and that word has
one of two values: it's either 0 or 1.
If it's 0, that means the lock is free
or sometimes we say it's unlocked or
it has been released
and if the value is 1
then the lock is said to be held or acquired or locked.
These are the common values that are typically used
and xv6 does that as well
okay, so
here is the structure that xv6 uses for a spin lock.
There are two other fields here
"name" and "cpu"
which you can see are just used for debugging.
So, here's what a spin lock looks like.
In addition to the key field
that tells the state of the lock.
We have a pointer to a string
which could be used for debugging
and we have this field called cpu
which points to some other structure.
Every core has a
structure associated with it, called a cpu structure
and this field contains a pointer to the
structure for the cpu that's currently holding the lock
okay, so the important functions on a spin lock
or any lock really
are acquire() and release()
In addition, we have a function that is
to be called when the lock is first created
that initializes the lock
basically it's passed the name that we associate with the lock.
Once the name is set, it does not change.
We've also got a function that's used for error checking
to determine whether the current core is holding the lock.
Each of these functions is passed a pointer
to one of these spinlock structs
So, it's passed a pointer like this pointer here
okay, to acquire the lock
typically, what we do
is we just set, we want to set the field to 1
but before we do that
we need to check to make sure that it's not currently being held
so our first pass at coding
the acquire() function might look like this
check to see whether the lock is free and if it is free, then set it to 1
and if it's not free, then loop back and keep trying
so these are spin locks
they spin, it's a tight loop that keeps checking
until it finds that the field is 0.
It sets it to 1 and then at that point
the lock is acquired.
Well, of course, this has a problem, if there are other threads that are executing concurrently.
In the case of xv6, we've got multiple cores
so this one particular field in memory
maybe accessed simultaneously by other cores
or perhaps if there's
thread switching going on within the single core
perhaps some other thread within the same core
is trying to access the same memory location
and we could have
two threads simultaneously check this field
and just happen to find that they are both
that if the lock is unlocked and then
simultaneously both set the lock to 1
and so that's going to cause a problem because
they both now think they are holding the lock
so we have to
find another way to do it, this code will not work
and for that
the RISC-V architecture has an instruction called "amoswap"
atomic memory operation swap
and this single instruction will do two things
it will copy a value into a word of memory
and at the same time
it will retrieve the previous value
of that word and it will do it without interruption
it will
not allow any other threads, or any other instructions
whether from this core or another core
to do anything between
the retrieval of the value and the setting of the value
so here's how we're gonna use that
atomic memory swap operation to
correct the problem that this code has.
We're going to execute the
atomic swap operation which I'm indicating
schematically here.
We're going to write a 1 into the location
and we're also going to retrieve
the old value, the previous value.
If the previous value
was 0, then we're done, we have acquired the lock.
But if the previous value was not 0
well, it must have been 1, because there are no other options.
Then somebody else was previously holding the lock
so we have to loop back and try again
so then we spin until finally we find the previous value was 0
and we then have acquired the lock
The release() operation is pretty straightforward.
We just copy the unlocked value of 0 into the word
this doesn't, it's hard to imagine how copying
value into a single location of memory could be anything but atomic, so in some systems this is implemented
it's just a single memory store operation.
Okay, now let's look at the code for
the acquire operation.
First of all, we can take care of the init operation
this is code that's coming from the spinlock.c file
this is code that's coming from the spinlock.c file.
To initialize a spinlock
we pass a pointer to the structure
and the name.
We set the name field and it never changes after that.
We also set the cpu field to null, because the lock is not held
and we set its initial value to 0.
Here is the code for the acquire() function
and here, right here, we see the
while loop that does exactly what I described previously.
This magic  __sync_lock_test_and_set() is
going to be turned into some assembly code
and the comment here is indicating that the amoswap
instruction is going to be happening
and it talks about some registers
But essentially we're passing it a pointer to the word that we want to update
and we're passing it the new value which is 1
and this function is going to return the old value
and we're checking to see whether it is 0 or not
and if it was not 0
then we repeat this while loop
and if it was 0, then we acquire the lock and we're done.
Now, there are a couple of other things I want to mention about this function.
First, once we acquire the lock, we are storing
into the cpu field.
Every core has a structure associated with it
so there are in fact 8 cores, so there are 8 structures
and this function here
will retrieve a pointer, or return a pointer to
the structure for the core that's currently executing
so we're just saving that here.
Up here, we are
checking to see whether before we
acquire the lock whether we already
whether it's already
being held by us
so we'll see the holding() function in just a second
if it is, then something is drastically the matter, so we cause an error message.
Then we've got this
__sync_synchronize() going on here
so tell the C compiler and the processor
not to move loads or stores past this point
to ensure that the critical section's memory references
happen strictly after
the lock is acquired
this is a fence instruction.
So, we want to prevent the compiler from doing optimizations.
It might in fact reorder things
and that is not acceptable though
anything that's supposed to be done
after we acquire this lock
after this while loop completes
must be done after that
so that's what this  __sync_synchronize() does, it forces
the compiler to emit code and the processor to
execute that code in such a way that everything
that is supposed to happen before
this point is completed
and everything that is supposed to happen
after this point
is not started until after this point.
We see one other thing here that's kind of unusual
and that is push_off()
the comment says disable interrupts to avoid deadlock
Holy Smoke! (天哪!)  What's that?
I mean, isn't this a lock situation here?
Why are interrupts involved at all?
I'll come back to that in a minute
so I'm going to just leave you in suspense.
But first let's take a look at the release operation
We do a quick check to make sure that we are in fact
holding this lock
and if not, we print an error message
and then we're going to be releasing it down here
and so we might as well go ahead and set the cpu field
to know at this point
and
here we are copying
the 0 into this field.
They're using an amoswap instruction to do it with this
__sync_lock_release()
but like I said, it's hard to imagine how a
normal stored of memory could be anything less than atomic
and we've got
pop_off()
Well, we've got the  __sync_synchronize() here, up here
which makes sure that anything that's supposed to happen
before we release the lock
actually finishes
and that anything that's
and only after we finish that, do we actually
set the lock field to 0.
so, pop_off() is
a partner, a dual of push_off() and
so, what it does is it enables interrupts
and I'll come back to that
in a second, but
first let's look at this holding() function
just to complete this code
This just checks to see whether
the current core that's executing this is holding the lock.
okay
it looks at the value of the field and if it's 1 and
the cpu is the same as this core
then it returns true and otherwise it returns false.
A spinlock should never be held for a long period of time,
Imagine a situation where one core is holding a lock
and another core wants to acquire that lock.
Well, the acquire() function is going to be spinning in a
tight loop, waiting for the lock to become free.
So, as a general rule of thumb, you should always
plan to release the lock soon after it's acquired.
In particular
we don't want the thread that's holding the lock to go to
sleep or to get time sliced.
There are other techniques for locking
in xv6 we have the sleep() and the wakeup() function
and these can be used in situations where
the lock needs to be held for a long period of time.
Locks are used to protect shared data.
Actually the xv6 documentation has some interesting wisdom.
They point out that locks really protect
constraints and I think that's a nice way to put it.
But in any case
we usually are almost always see this particular pattern here.
We acquire the lock
then we access the shared data
and then we release the lock.
The code here is often called a critical section (临界区).
In other words, it's critical
it can only be executed by one thread at a time
so therefore this code is protected by a lock.
Let's look at a quick example and I'm going to imagine
input a character, input that's
coming from somewhere and going to someplace else.
So, perhaps we have a keyboard
and every time the user types on the keyboard
an interrupt handler wakes up and adds a character to
a shared buffer.
So the buffer is the shared memory item
and it's going to be a FIFO queue.
So the data goes in one end
and there's some other thread that is reading from the buffer
when it needs a character, it just
needs to access this shared data structure
which we will need to protect
and in this example we will protect it with a spinlock.
So here's the code that we might see in the handler.
It acquires the spinlock
adds a character to the buffer
and then releases the lock.
The thread that wants to get input is going to acquire
the lock, so it can access the shared buffer
remove a character and release the lock.
I'm not going to be concerned with what happens
if the buffer is completely full
or completely empty.
The handler is called when
someone types a character on the keyboard
and interrupt handlers
begin with the trap processing
which will disable interrupts
and then they'll do some stuff basically
this stuff here in the case of our example
and then
they will return to the interrupted code with the
sret instruction which will re-enable interrupts
so we might imagine a thread "T" that's running like this
an interrupt happens as a result of a key being pressed
the handler runs
and then when it's done, adding the character to the buffer
it returns to the interrupted thread whatever it was
and continues.
Well, so you can imagine this situation
if "T"
happens to be this thread here that acquires a lock
and then at just the wrong moment the interupt comes in
from the keyboard and the handler is invoked
and the first thing the handler does is try to acquire that lock
well
it will wait until the lock is released
but unfortunately the thread that is holding the lock
is waiting for the handler to complete
so we've got a deadlock situation.
In operating systems
we need to remember that if anything
if any combination of events
can possibly theoretically happen
it's best to assume that it will happen
no matter how unlikely or how rarely you think the event is.
Our first approach to solving the problem of deadlock
is to disable interrupts in the acquire() function
and then to re-enable them in the release() function.
So we don't have a situation like this:
if "T" acquires a lock, it will
disable interrupt, so it cannot have a situation where
some other thread on that same core is trying to acquire the lock.
This also has an additional benefit:
we don't want to hold spinlocks for very long
so by disabling interrupts
we are preventing timeslicing from happening
while the lock is held
and we are preventing interrupt processing from occurring
basically we're allowing the core
to focus on the thread that is holding the lock and to
complete its critical section without interruption
quickly and then release the lock
but now we have another problem:
What if interrupts are already disabled?
For example, in our handler code
we have interrupts disabled and
for a number of reasons we don't want to re-enable
interrupts prematurely before we get to the system return instruction.
We might also have several spinlocks that we need to acquire
and so we have
perhaps three acquire() functions being called in a row
and for each one of those will have three release()
functions, but the first release() will
disable, sorry, will re-enable interrupts
and that might not be quite what we want
so essentially we want this release()
to return the interrupt status to whatever it was
before the acquire() happened
and we want to accommodate nested calls
that is we want to accommodate several acquire() function calls
followed by several release() function calls
and our solution to this problem is simple:
We're going to use a counter
and that counter happens to be called "noff"
and it's specific to a core
this variable will be held in the cpu structure.
Each core has its own cpu structure
and each one will contain its own counter.
So the acquire() function will
increment the counter and then disable the interrupts
perhaps they were already disabled
but they will be after the acquire() for sure
and what's release() going to do ?
Well, release() is going to decrement the count
and to handle the nested case if it goes back to 0
then it's time to consider re-enabling them
More precisely
we need to ask whether they were previously enabled
before the first
call to acquire()
so if the count is 0 and they were previously enabled
then we will re-enable them
that previously enabled status is kept in a variable called
interrupt enable "intena", I guess
and so we all
we will remember the previous interrupt status
before the first call to acquire()
in this variable which is a part of the cpu structure.
Okay, now we can take a look at the code for
push_off() and pop_off().
Remember that in the acquire() function shown here
the first thing we did was
call push_off() to disable interrupts to avoid deadlock
so now we know what that means
and in the release(), we also end up calling
pop_off()
Here's the code for release()
and right before we return
we re-enable interrupts if appropriate.
So, let's take a look at push_off() and pop_off().
push_off() is called by acquire()
we immediately turn interrupts off.
We disable interrupts.
Well, first we
find out what the previous status of the interrupts was
that's called "old"
and then here we're accessing the cpu structure
and if this is the first call to acquire()
that is, that the counter is already is previously 0
and we're going to save the old status
but in any case we're going to increment the counter
pop_off() is as you'd expect
pretty similar.
We're accessing the counter and the "intena" variable here
so we start by getting a pointer to the cpu structure
and then we decrement the counter at this point here
and if it went to 0
and interrupts were previously enabled
then we turn them back on at this point.
We also have some
error checking here.
If for some reason we call pop_off() and interrupts
are already enabled something drastically the matter
so we print an error message.
And we also make sure that the counter is not 0 or smaller
that would also be some sort of an error condition.
Okay, that's it for spinlocks.
See you in the next video.